<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<teiCorpus>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lirimix Corpus</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Lirimix is a web application diplaying a TEI corpus encoded by Jean-Luc Mirepoix
                    for the python course in the frame of the Master TNAH at the Ecole Nationale des
                    Chartes</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This corpus gather lyrics (in irish: "liricí") of Irish songs from the War of
                    Independance period, going from the Easter Uprising of 1916 to the Civil War
                    (1922-1923).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <!-- An index of the authors -->
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person idf="102">
                        <persName xml:lang="ga">
                            <forename>Pádraig Anraí Mac Piarais</forename>
                            <note>Nasc le Vicipéid
                                    <link>https://ga.wikipedia.org/wiki/P%C3%A1draig_Mac_Piarais</link></note>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="en">
                            <forename>Patrick Henry Pearse </forename>
                            <note>Wikipedia Link
                                    <link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Pearse</link></note>
                        </persName>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl n='1'>Óró, sé do bheatha 'bhaile</bibl>
                            <bibl n='4'>Amhrán na bhFiann</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </person>
                    <person idf="101">
                        <persName xml:lang="ga">
                            <forename>Cathal Ó Néill </forename>
                            <note>Lúb ar lár</note>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="en">
                            <forename>Charles O'Neill </forename>
                            <note>Wikipedia Link
                                    <link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foggy_Dew_(Irish_ballad)</link></note>
                        </persName>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl n='2'>The Foggy Dew</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </person>
                    <person idf="103">
                        <persName xml:lang="ga">
                            <forename>Peadar Ó Cearnaígh </forename>
                            <note>Nasc le Vicipéid
                                    <link>https://ga.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peadar_%C3%93_Cearnaigh</link></note>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="en">
                            <forename>Peadar Kearney </forename>
                            <note>Wikipedia Link
                                    <link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peadar_Kearney</link></note>
                        </persName>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl n='3'>Down by the Glenside</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </person>
                    <person idf="104">
                        <persName xml:lang="ga">
                            <forename>Patrick "Paddy" Heeney </forename>
                            <note>Lúb ar lár</note>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="en">
                            <forename>Patrick "Paddy" Heeney </forename>
                            <note>Wikipedia Link
                                    <link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Heeney</link></note>
                        </persName>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl n='4'>Amhrán na bhFiann</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </person>
                    <person idf="105">
                        <persName xml:lang="ga">
                            <forename>Liam 'Coinneach' Ó Rinn </forename>
                            <note>Lúb ar lár</note>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="en">
                            <forename>William 'Coinneach' J. Ring </forename>
                            <note>Wikipedia Link
                                    <link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liam_%C3%93_Rinn</link></note>
                        </persName>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl n='4'>Amhrán na bhFiann</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <TEI n="1">
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">Óró, sé do bheatha 'bhaile</title>
                    <title type="alternative">Dord na bhFiann</title>
                    <title type="alternative">An Dord Féinne</title>
                    <author corresp="102"><name xml:lang='en'>Patrick Henry Pearse</name><name xml:lang='ga'>Pádraig Anraí Mac Piarais</name></author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <p>Texte édité dans le cadre d'un devoir par Jean-Luc Mirepoix, master 2 TNAH à
                        l'Ecole nationale des Chartes</p>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <recordingStmt>
                        <recording dur="PT03M20S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Derek Warfield</name>
                                <name>The Young Wolfe Tones</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media url="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kmX56cTAfio"
                                mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A youtube video uploaded by the Young Wolfe Tones</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="2011-10-27">27/10/2011</date>
                        </recording>
                        <recording dur="PT06M12S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Seo Linn</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media url="https://youtu.be/bzXswoAUi0U" mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A youtube clip uploaded by the Conradh na Gaeilge (Gaelic
                                    League)</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="2016-02-25">25/02/2016</date>
                        </recording>
                        <recording dur="PT02M32S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Denis Cox</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media
                                url="https://www.itma.ie/digital-library/sound/oro-se-do-bheatha-bhaile-cox"
                                mimeType="audio/mp3">
                                <desc>78rpm audio disc hold by the Irish Traditional Music
                                    Archive/Taisce Cheol Dúchais Éireann under the reference
                                    16963-SE</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date from="1930" to="1939">1930's, precise date unknown</date>
                        </recording>
                    </recordingStmt>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <front>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <p>Like many folk songs, the origins of this song are obscure, but several
                        different uses of the tune and chorus can be identified. In 1884 Mr. Francis
                        Hogan of Brenormore, near Carrick-on-Suir, then “well over seventy years of
                        age”, reported that “this song used to be played at the ‘Hauling Home,’ or
                        the bringing home of a wife”. The "hauling home" was a ceremony that took
                        place a month after a wedding when a bride was brought to live in her new
                        husband's home. This version consists only of the chorus. Énrí Ó Muirġeasa
                        also records a similar refrain in 1915 from the Barony of Farney, “but the
                        song to which it belonged was lost before my time”. There is no mention of
                        “hauling home” and the line that P. W. Joyce gives as thá tu maith le rátha
                        (“’tis you are happy with prosperity [in store for you]”) is instead Tá tú
                        amuiġ le ráiṫċe (“You’ve been gone three months”). This song has also been
                        associated with the Jacobite cause as the traditional version mentions
                        Séarlas Óg ("Young Charles" in Irish), referring to Charles Edward Louis
                        John Casimir Sylvester Severino Maria Stuart (Bonnie Prince Charlie) and
                        dating the song to the third Jacobite rising of 1745-6. The tune appears as
                        number 1425 in George Petrie's The Complete Collection of Irish Music (1855)
                        under the title Ó ro! ’sé do ḃeaṫa a ḃaile (modern script: Ó ro! ’sé do
                        bheatha a bhaile) and is marked “Ancient clan march.” It can also be found
                        at number 983 (also marked “Ancient Clan March”) and as a fragment at number
                        1056, titled Welcome home Prince Charley. In the early 20th century it
                        received new verses by the nationalist poet Padraig Pearse and was often
                        sung by members of the Irish Volunteers during the Easter Rising. It was
                        also sung as a fast march during the Irish War of Independence. Since 1916
                        it has also been known under various other titles, notably Dord na bhFiann
                        (Call of the Fighters) or An Dord Féinne. The latter title is associated
                        with Pearse in particular. This version features the pirate or "Great Sea
                        Warrior" Gráinne Ní Mháille (Grace O'Malley), a formidable power on the west
                        coast of Ireland in the late 16th century. Pearse shows his knowledge of the
                        Jacobite version in the way he adapts it to the new independence cause. He
                        emphasises the Irishness of the fighters by substituting native Gráinne for
                        foreign Prince Charlie and changing Béidh siad leis-sean Franncaigh is
                        Spáinnigh (“They’ll be with him, French and Spanish”) to Gaeil féin 's ní
                        Francaigh ná Spáinnigh (“Gaels they, and neither French nor Spaniard”). </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="ga">
                    <p>Amhrán Éireannach is ea Oró, 'Sé do Bheatha 'Bhaile. Tá cáil air mar amhrán
                        reibiliúnach. Tháinig an t-amhrán ó am an dara éirí amach Seacaibíteach. Ba
                        é 'Bonnie Prince Charles' an Séarlas Óg san amhrán Scríobh Pádraig Mac
                        Piarais véarsaí breise don amhrán. </p>
                </div>
            </front>
            <body>
                <div type="song" xml:lang="ga">
                    <lg n="1" type="verse">
                        <l n="1">’Sé do bheatha, a bhean ba léanmhar</l>
                        <l n="2">do bé ár gcreach tú bheith i ngéibhinn</l>
                        <l n="3">do dhúiche bhreá i seilbh meirleach</l>
                        <l n="4">'s tú díolta leis na Gallaibh.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="5">Óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="6">óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="7">óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="8">anois ar theacht an tsamhraidh.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="2" type="verse">
                        <l n="9">Tá Gráinne Mhaol ag teacht thar sáile</l>
                        <l n="10">óglaigh armtha léi mar gharda,</l>
                        <l n="11">Gaeil iad féin is ní Francaigh ná Spáinnigh</l>
                        <l n="12">'s cuirfidh siad ruaig ar Ghallaibh.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="13">Óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="14">óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="15">óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="16">anois ar theacht an tsamhraidh.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="3" type="verse">
                        <l n="17">A bhuí le Rí na bhFeart go bhfeiceam</l>
                        <l n="18">muna mbeam beo ina dhiaidh ach seachtain</l>
                        <l n="19">Gráinne Mhaol agus míle gaiscíoch</l>
                        <l n="20">ag fógairt fáin ar Ghallaibh.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="21">Óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="22">óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="23">óró, sé do bheatha bhaile</l>
                        <l n="24">anois ar theacht an tsamhraidh.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI n="2">
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">The Foggy Dew</title>
                    <title type="alternative">Down the Glen</title>
                    <author corresp="101"><name xml:lang='en'>Charles O'Neill</name><name xml:lang='ga'>Cathal Ó Néill</name></author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <p>Texte édité dans le cadre d'un devoir par Jean-Luc Mirepoix, master 2 TNAH à
                        l'Ecole nationale des Chartes</p>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <recordingStmt>
                        <recording dur="PT03M00S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Jim Dwyer</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media
                                url="https://www.itma.ie/digital-library/sound/the-foggy-dew-jim-dwyer"
                                mimeType="audio/mp3">
                                <desc>78rpm audio disc hold by the Irish Traditional Music
                                    Archive/Taisce Cheol Dúchais Éireann under the reference
                                    235071</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="1938-07-12">12/07/1938</date>
                        </recording>
                        <recording dur="PT03M23S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>The Dubliners</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media url="https://youtu.be/r8Gq1XAdHJM" mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A youtube clip uploaded on the official youtube chanel of the
                                    Dubliners</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="1967">1967</date>
                        </recording>
                        <recording dur="PT05M33S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Daoirí Farrell</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media url="https://youtu.be/2lw1T-M_FNc" mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A youtube clip uploaded on the youtube chanel of the irish
                                    public service channel RTÉ One</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="2019-04-26">26/04/2019</date>
                        </recording>
                    </recordingStmt>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <front>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <p>“Foggy Dew” was written by Fr (later in life) Canon Charles O’Neill from
                        Portglenone, County Antrim (1887–1963), a parish priest of Kilcoo and later
                        Newcastle, County Down, sometime after 1919 when he was a curate at St.
                        Peter's Cathedral, Belfast. The music is from a manuscript that was in
                        possession of Kathleen Dallat, sister of Michael Dallat of Ballycastle. That
                        manuscript gives Carl Hardebeck as the arranger. It is the same air as the
                        traditional love song The Moorlough Shore. "The Foggy Dew" is a product of
                        the political situation in Ireland in the aftermath of the Easter Rising and
                        World War I. Approximately 210,000 Irishmen joined up and served in the
                        British forces during the war. This created mixed feelings for many Irish
                        people, particularly for those with nationalist sympathies. While they
                        broadly supported the British war effort, they also felt that one of the
                        moral justifications for the war, "the freedom of small nations" like
                        Belgium and Serbia, should also be applied to Ireland, which at that time
                        was under British rule. The 1915 Gallipoli slaughter of the young and mainly
                        middle-class Irishmen who had joined up in response to John Redmond's call
                        turned many people against the war. In 1916, Irish patriots led by James
                        Connolly and Patrick Pearse, taking advantage of Britain being occupied by
                        World War I, seized some of the major buildings in Dublin including the
                        General Post Office, while others came out in Ashbourne and Galway in the
                        Easter Rising. The brutal response to the Rising, and the execution of its
                        leaders that followed, marked a turning point for many Irish people. The
                        public revulsion at the executions added to the growing sense of alienation
                        from the British Government. Canon O'Neill reflected this alienation when he
                        wrote The Foggy Dew commemorating the few hundred brave men who had risen
                        out against what was then the most powerful empire in the world. In 1919, he
                        attended the first sitting of the new Irish Parliament, Dáil. The names of
                        the elected members were called out, but many were absent. Their names were
                        answered by the reply faoi ghlas ag na Gaill – "locked up by the foreigner".
                        These events had a profound effect on O'Neill and some time after this he
                        wrote The Foggy Dew telling the story of the Easter Rising and reflecting
                        the thoughts of many Irish people at the time who now believed that the
                        Irishmen who fought for Britain during the war should have stayed home and
                        fought for Irish independence instead. O'Neill sums up this feeling in the
                        line ‘Twas far better to die ‘neath an Irish sky, Than at Suvla or Sud el
                        Bar. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="ga">
                    <p>Nil é féin aistrithe fós.</p>
                </div>
            </front>
            <body>
                <div type="song" xml:lang="en">
                    <lg n="1" type="verse">
                        <l n="1">As down the glen one Easter morn to a city fair rode I</l>
                        <l n="2">There Armed lines of marching men in squadrons passed me by</l>
                        <l n="3">No pipe did hum nor battle drum did sound its loud tattoo</l>
                        <l n="4">But the Angelus Bell o'er the Liffey's swell rang out through the
                            foggy dew</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="2" type="verse">
                        <l n="5">Right proudly high over Dublin Town they hung out the flag of
                            war</l>
                        <l n="6">'Twas better to die 'neath an Irish sky than at Suvla or
                            Sud-El-Bar</l>
                        <l n="7">And from the plains of Royal Meath strong men came hurrying
                            through</l>
                        <l n="8">While Britannia's Huns, with their long range guns sailed in
                            through the foggy dew</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="3" type="verse">
                        <l n="9">'Twas England bade our Wild Geese go, that small nations might be
                            free;</l>
                        <l n="10">Their lonely graves are by Suvla's waves or the fringe of the
                            great North Sea.</l>
                        <l n="11">Oh, had they died by Pearse's side or fought with Cathal
                            Brugha</l>
                        <l n="12">Their graves we'd keep where the Fenians sleep, 'neath the shroud
                            of the foggy dew.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="4" type="verse">
                        <l n="13">Oh the night fell black, and the rifles' crack made Perfidious
                            Albion reel</l>
                        <l n="14">In the leaden rain, seven tongues of flame did shine o'er the
                            lines of steel</l>
                        <l n="15">By each shining blade a prayer was said, that to Ireland her sons
                            be true</l>
                        <l n="16">But when morning broke, still the war flag shook out its folds in
                            the foggy dew</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="5" type="verse">
                        <l n="17">Oh the bravest fell, and the Requiem bell rang mournfully and
                            clear</l>
                        <l n="18">For those who died that Easter tide in the spring time of the
                            year</l>
                        <l n="19">And the world did gaze, in deep amaze, at those fearless men, but
                            few,</l>
                        <l n="20">Who bore the fight that freedom's light might shine through the
                            foggy dew</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="6" type="verse">
                        <l n="21">As back through the glen I rode again and my heart with grief was
                            sore</l>
                        <l n="22">For I parted then with valiant men whom I never shall see more</l>
                        <l n="23">But to and fro in my dreams I go and I kneel and pray for you,</l>
                        <l n="24">For slavery fled, O glorious dead, when you fell in the foggy dew.
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI n="3">
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">Down by the Glenside</title>
                    <title type="alternative">The Bold Fenian Men</title>
                    <author corresp="103"><name xml:lang='en'>Peadar Kearney</name><name xml:lang='ga'>Peadar Ó Cearnaígh</name></author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <p>Texte édité dans le cadre d'un devoir par Jean-Luc Mirepoix, master 2 TNAH à
                        l'Ecole nationale des Chartes</p>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <recordingStmt>
                        <recording dur="PT02M54S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Delia Murphy</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media
                                url="https://www.itma.ie/digital-library/sound/down-by-the-glenside-delia-murphy"
                                mimeType="audio/mp3">
                                <desc>78rpm audio disc hold by the Irish Traditional Music
                                    Archive/Taisce Cheol Dúchais Éireann under the reference
                                    235043</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="1939">1939</date>
                        </recording>
                        <recording dur="PT03M23S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>The Dubliners</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media url="https://youtu.be/eNBAoWULT_8" mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A youtube clip uploaded on the official youtube chanel of the
                                    Dubliners</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="1977">1977</date>
                        </recording>
                        <recording dur="PT04M04S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Richard Dyer-Bennett</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media url="https://youtu.be/vMfYFrDT_-M" mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A youtube clip uploaded provided by Smithsonian Folkways
                                    Recordings</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="1955">1955</date>
                        </recording>
                    </recordingStmt>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <front>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <p> "Down by the Glenside (The Bold Fenian Men)" is an Irish rebel song written
                        by Peadar Kearney, an Irish Republican and composer of numerous rebel songs,
                        including "The Soldier's Song" ("Amhrán na bhFiann"), now the Irish National
                        Anthem and "The Tri-coloured Ribbon". Kearney was a member of the Irish
                        Republican Brotherhood, popularly known as the Fenians. He wrote the song
                        about the time of the 1916 Rising. It evokes the memory of the
                        freedom-fighters of the previous generation (strong, manly forms...eyes with
                        hope gleaming), as recalled by an old woman down by the glenside. It is
                        effectively a call to arms for a generation of Irishmen accustomed to
                        political nationalism. Three verses to this song were sung by Ken Curtis and
                        The Sons of the Pioneers in the 1950 John Ford movie Rio Grande. Richard
                        Dyer-Bennet recorded the song on his first self produced LP Richard
                        Dyer-Bennet 1, (1955). The song became popular again in the 1960s, when it
                        was recorded by The Clancy Brothers. It has since been recorded by numerous
                        artists, including The Dubliners, Cherish The Ladies, Omnia, Screaming
                        Orphans, Jim McCann, Harry O'Donoghue, and The Wolfe Tones. The song is also
                        sung in the first episode of the BBC series Days of Hope, written by Jim
                        Allen and directed by Ken Loach. An Irish barmaid is forced to sing after
                        being sexually harassed by British soldiers and impresses them with her
                        song. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="ga">
                    <p>Nil é féin aistrithe fós.</p>
                </div>
            </front>
            <body>
                <div type="song" xml:lang="en">
                    <lg n="1" type="verse">
                        <l n="1">'Twas down by the glenside, I met an old woman</l>
                        <l n="2">A-plucking young nettles, she ne’er saw me coming</l>
                        <l n="3">I listened a while to the song she was humming</l>
                        <l n="4">Glory O, Glory O, to the bold Fenian men</l>

                    </lg>
                    <lg n="2" type="verse">
                        <l n="5">'Tis fifty long years since I saw the moon beaming</l>
                        <l n="6">On strong manly forms, on eyes with hope gleaming</l>
                        <l n="7">I see them again, sure, in all my sad dreaming</l>
                        <l n="8">Glory O, Glory O, to the bold Fenian men</l>

                    </lg>
                    <lg n="3" type="verse">
                        <l n="9">When I was a young girl, their marching and drilling</l>
                        <l n="10">Awoke in the glenside sounds awesome and thrilling</l>
                        <l n="11">They loved dear old Ireland, to die they were willing</l>
                        <l n="12">Glory O, Glory O, to the bold Fenian men</l>

                    </lg>
                    <lg n="4" type="verse">
                        <l n="13">Some died by the glenside, some died near a stranger</l>
                        <l n="14">And wise men have told us their cause was a failure</l>
                        <l n="15">But they fought for old Ireland and never feared danger</l>
                        <l n="16">Glory O, Glory O, to the bold Fenian men</l>

                    </lg>
                    <lg n="5" type="verse">
                        <l n="17">I passed on my way, God be praised that I met her</l>
                        <l n="18">Be life long or short, sure I'll never forget her</l>
                        <l n="19">We may have brave men, but we'll never have better</l>
                        <l n="20">Glory O, Glory O, to the bold Fenian men</l>

                    </lg>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI n="4">
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">Amhrán na bhFiann</title>
                    <title type="alternative">A Soldier's Song</title>
                    <title type="alternative">Amhrán Náisiúnta na hÉireann</title>
                    <title type="alternative">Sinn Féin anthem</title>
                    <author corresp="102"><name xml:lang='en'>Patrick Henry Pearse</name><name xml:lang='ga'>Pádraig Anraí Mac Piarais</name></author>
                    <author corresp="105"><name xml:lang='en'>William 'Coinneach' J. Ring</name><name xml:lang='ga'>Liam 'Coinneach' Ó Rinn</name></author>
                    <author corresp="104"><name xml:lang='en'>Patrick "Paddy" Heeney</name><name xml:lang='ga'>Patrick "Paddy" Heeney </name></author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <p>Texte édité dans le cadre d'un devoir par Jean-Luc Mirepoix, master 2 TNAH à
                        l'Ecole nationale des Chartes</p>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <recordingStmt>
                        <recording dur="PT01M44S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Senan Dunne</name>
                                <name>Darren Byrne</name>
                                <name>Gloria Chóir</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media
                                url="https://www.gov.ie/en/publication/52a628-the-national-anthem/"
                                mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A sign-language version uploaded on the official Irish
                                    governement website</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="2018-04">04/2018</date>
                        </recording>
                        <recording dur="PT03M10S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Máirtín de Cógáin</name>
                                <name>Gregory Grene</name>
                                <name> Brian OhAirt</name>
                                <name>Alex Grene</name>
                                <name>Chris Buckley</name>
                                <name>Joseph Carmichael</name>
                                <name>Daniel Mehalko</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media url="https://youtu.be/geeZ7NJnxPk" mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A youtube clip uploaded by the Celtic Cultural Center of
                                    Austin, Texas</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="2016">2016</date>
                        </recording>
                        <recording dur="PT01M56S">
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Artist</resp>
                                <name>Pupils from Our Lady of Lourdes NS Bunclody, Co.
                                    Wexford</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <media url="https://youtu.be/1PzXeTeRyek" mimeType="video/mp4">
                                <desc>A youtube clip uploaded on the channel of the Our Lady of
                                    Lourdes School's channel</desc>
                            </media>
                            <date when="2015-11-25">25/11/2015</date>
                        </recording>
                    </recordingStmt>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <front>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <p> Amhrán na bhFiann", called "The Soldier's Song" in English, is Ireland's
                        national anthem. The music was composed by Peadar Kearney and Patrick
                        Heeney, the original English lyrics by Kearney, and the Irish-language
                        translation, now usually heard, by Liam Ó Rinn. The song has three verses,
                        but only the choral refrain is used as the national anthem. The Presidential
                        Salute, played when the President of Ireland arrives at an official
                        engagement, consists of the first four bars of the national anthem
                        immediately followed by the last five. </p>
                    <p> The song, as "A Soldier's Song", was composed "early in 1910 or late in
                        1909", with words by Peadar Kearney, and music by his childhood friend and
                        neighbour Patrick Heeney, who had collaborated on songs since 1903. Kearney
                        assisted Heeney in setting the refrain. Heeney composed it with his
                        melodeon. Seán Rogan, later of the Irish Citizen Army, may also have helped
                        with the music, and first wrote it in musical notation. Kearney wrote much
                        of the text in the Swiss Café at the corner of O'Connell Street and North
                        Earl Street. The first draft of the text, handwritten on copybook paper,
                        sold at auction in Dublin in 2006 for €760,000. After being rejected by The
                        United Irishman, Bulmer Hobson's magazine Irish Freedom published the text
                        in 1912. Whelan and Son of Ormond Quay, Dublin, published the lyrics for
                        sale as a flysheet. It was used as marching song by the Irish Volunteers and
                        Seamus Hughes first sang it in public at a Volunteer fundraising concert. It
                        was sung by rebels in the General Post Office (GPO) during the Easter Rising
                        of 1916. Its popularity increased among rebels held in Frongoch internment
                        camp after the Rising. The sheet music was first published in late 1916 by
                        Whelan and Son, in an arrangement by Cathal Mac Dubhghaill (Cecil Grange
                        MacDowell). In December 1916 in New York City, Victor Herbert published his
                        own piano and orchestral arrangements under the title "Soldiers of Erin, the
                        Rallying Song of the Irish Volunteers", on the instigation of R. F.
                        O'Reilly, an Irish priest. O'Reilly arranged for proceeds to go to the
                        Gaelic League, but paid royalties to Kearney and Heeney once he discovered
                        they were the authors. With later cheques from the US, Kearney earned "not
                        much more than £100". By 1917, according to Séumas Robinson, the song was
                        being parodied by British soldiers in Ireland. Éamon de Valera's platform at
                        the June 1917 East Clare by-election featured a large banner with the
                        opening two lines. That October the Irish Volunteers allied with Sinn Féin
                        under de Valera and during the Irish War of Independence (1919–21) the
                        Volunteers evolved into the Irish Republican Army (IRA). The song's
                        popularity led to its being called the "Sinn Féin anthem". Copies were
                        confiscated by British security forces as seditious. Carl Hardebeck played
                        it unannounced on Low Sunday 1918 in St Peter's Cathedral, Belfast. Victor
                        Herbert's version was well known to Irish Americans by 1919, when de Valera
                        arrived as President of Dáil Éireann of the self-proclaimed Irish Republic.
                        In the 1922–23 Civil War, the IRA split into the "National Army" of the
                        nascent Irish Free State and the "Irregulars" loyal to the defunct Republic.
                        Both sides continued to sing "The Soldier's Song". After the war, it
                        remained popular as an Army tune, and was played at many military functions.
                        Official adoption The Free State did not initially adopt any official state
                        anthem. The delicate political state in the aftermath of the Civil War
                        provoked a desire to avoid controversy. Ex-unionists continued to regard
                        "God Save the King" as the national anthem, as it had been for the rest of
                        the British Empire. The fact that "The Soldier's Song" described Irishmen
                        fighting a foreign foe allowed it to overlook the painful memory of the
                        Civil War. W. T. Cosgrave, 1922–32 President of the Executive Council,
                        avoided explicitly making it the national anthem for fear of exacerbating
                        the antipathy for the Free State held by unionists in Northern Ireland. As
                        with the Irish tricolour, the government did not want to disassociate the
                        state from the anthem for fear of leaving a potent symbol available for its
                        republican opponents to claim. "The Soldier's Song" was widely if
                        unofficially sung by nationalists. Public perception that it was officially
                        recognised sprang from a concert on 3 February 1924 at the Theatre Royal,
                        Dublin by the Irish Army music school under its German-born director,
                        Colonel Fritz Brase. As an encore to the concert, Brasé conducted "Irish
                        March, no.1", his medley of Irish patriotic airs, which ended with that of
                        "The Soldier's Song". Most dignitaries present stood up at this point,
                        including Governor-General Tim Healy, Cosgrave and most of the Executive
                        Council, although Richard Mulcahy remained seated. On 28 April 1924,
                        Cosgrave expressed opposition to replacing "The Soldier's Song", which was
                        provisionally used within the State. Sean Lester, Publicist at the
                        Department of External Affairs considered "The Soldier's Song" to be "hardly
                        suitable in words or music" and favoured the music, though not the words, of
                        "Let Erin Remember". This was used as the anthem for the state at the 1924
                        Olympics in Paris, and other events abroad for the next two years. The
                        Dublin Evening Mail held contests in 1924 and 1925 to find verses for a new
                        anthem; the first produced no sufficiently good entry, and the second's
                        winning entry was soon forgotten. There was concern that the lack of an
                        official anthem was giving unionists an opportunity to persist with "God
                        Save the King". Ewan Morris writes, "While some, perhaps many, nationalists
                        undoubtedly disliked 'The soldier's song', few would have objected so
                        strongly as to refuse to honour it as the national anthem. But for
                        ex-unionists 'The soldier's song' remained anathema, and 'God save the king'
                        continued to be the national anthem they honoured." By 1926 foreign
                        diplomats' protocol offices were requesting copies of the anthem's score. On
                        12 July 1926, the Executive Council decided to adopt it as the National
                        Anthem, with Cosgrave the driving force in the decision. He wrote to Lester,
                        "there must be uniformity in regard to the national anthem and that for the
                        present the 'Soldier’s song' is to be used for this purpose both at home and
                        abroad". The decision was not publicised. On 20 June 1926, Osmond Esmonde
                        asked President Cosgrave what the National Anthem was, but the Ceann
                        Comhairle Michael Hayes ruled 'If the Deputy desires to investigate any
                        problem in regard to the National Anthem, he cannot ask a question of the
                        President. The President cannot be asked to define what is the National
                        Anthem. It is not part of his functions.' Esmonde instead asked Minister for
                        Defence Peter Hughes what 'as far as the Army is concerned' was the National
                        Anthem. The draft response provided for Hughes stated that 'while no final
                        decision has been come to', "The Soldier's Song" was 'at present accepted as
                        the National Anthem', However, this wording was vetoed by Cosgrave, and in
                        the Dáil chamber Hughes responded simply 'The "Soldier's Song."' In 1928,
                        the Army band established the practice of playing only the chorus of the
                        song as the Anthem, because the longer version was discouraging audiences
                        from singing along. Also in 1928, Chief Justice Hugh Kennedy, returning from
                        an official trip to North America, reported that an official arrangement of
                        the music was "very badly needed" for circulation abroad. This was produced
                        in July 1929 by Colonel Fritz Brasé, director of the Army band. This
                        consisted only of the chorus, and was published under the title "The
                        Soldier's Song" rather than "A Soldier's Song", although variants such as
                        the "Soldiers' Song" continued to occur in later official documentation.
                        Copyright The national anthem was played at closedown by Radio Éireann from
                        its inception in 1926. The Catholic Truth Society of Ireland included it in
                        a 1929 publication commemorating the centenary of the Roman Catholic Relief
                        Act 1829. Cinemas and theatres played the anthem when closing from 1932
                        until 1972. Peadar Kearney, who had received royalties from sheet music
                        publishers, issued legal proceedings for royalties from those now performing
                        the anthem. He was joined by Michael Heeney, brother of Patrick Heeney, who
                        had died in 1911. In 1934, the Department of Finance acquired the copyright
                        of the song for the sum of £1,200 (£980 to the copyright holders plus £220
                        expenses). Copyright law changed in the 1950s, such that the government had
                        to reacquire copyright in 1965, for £2,500. Ruth Sherry states that it is
                        unclear whether the official anthem is the music alone or the text also;
                        however, the official 1934 Estimate of the amount required ... for the
                        acquisition by the state of copyright in the national anthem includes the
                        line item, 'Payment to the holders of copyright in the words and music of
                        the "Soldier's Song"' [emphasis added]. While the state held the copyright,
                        most requests for publication were accepted, "although several of a purely
                        commercial nature, such as its use in advertisements, were refused". As per
                        EU copyright law, the English lyrics' copyright expired on 1 January 2013,
                        following the 70th anniversary of Kearney's death. In 2016, three Fianna
                        Fáil senators introduced a private member's bill intended to restore the
                        state's copyright in the anthem. The ending of copyright also encourage the
                        Seanad to announce a public consultation on the anthem. </p>
                    <p> The Governor-General of the Irish Free State was the King's representative
                        and, as such, unionists considered that the appropriate official salute to
                        play was "God Save The King" rather than the Free State Anthem. At James
                        McNeill's 1928 inauguration, the Army band played "The Soldier's Song", but
                        that summer, at two events with unionist organisers, he was greeted by "God
                        Save The King". The Executive Council advised him that in future the Free
                        State anthem must be played. McNeill declined a June 1929 invitation to the
                        Trinity College sports when the college insisted that the British anthem was
                        its tradition. Unionists and people in Great Britain took this as a snub,
                        while for republican commentators it encapsulated the Free State's attempts
                        to suppress the truth about its subservience to Britain. A compromise
                        adopted in 1931 was that "The Soldier's Song" would mark the Governor
                        General's arrival and he would leave before the end of the sports, when "God
                        Save The King" would be played. In 1932, Éamon de Valera became President of
                        the Executive Council; as part of his campaign to abolish the office of
                        Governor-General, he forbade the Army band from playing "The Soldier's Song"
                        in McNeill's presence. The first ceremonial regulations for the Irish
                        Defence Forces, drawn up in 1926, provided that the official "Presidential
                        Salute" for the President of the Executive Council would be the first and
                        last eight bars of the national anthem. The 1937 Constitution renamed the
                        head of government Taoiseach, and introduced the office of President of
                        Ireland. The "Presidential Salute" has since 1937 been used for the
                        President of Ireland, who as head of state takes precedence over the
                        Taoiseach. The Taoiseach's salute is "Mór Chluana", an old Irish air to
                        which Osborn Bergin set "Amhrán Dóchais", which in the 1930s was often
                        suggested as a replacement national anthem. </p>
                    <p> The Irish translation was written by Liam Ó Rinn (1886–1943), later the
                        Chief Translator of the Oireachtas, who was involved in the Irish versions
                        of both the 1922 Constitution and the 1937 Constitution. Although Sherry
                        says the Irish version was first published in An tÓglach (the magazine of
                        the Irish Defence Forces) on 3 November 1923, an almost identical text was
                        printed in the Freeman's Journal on 3 April 1923, under Ó Rinn's pen name
                        "Coinneach". It may have been written as early as 1917. Ó Rinn's grandson
                        Nial claims Liam started work on a translation while interned in Frongoch
                        after the 1916 Rising. Several other translations had been made by 1923,
                        which Ó Rinn criticised as unreadable. These were in literary Classical
                        Irish, whereas Ó Rinn favoured the living vernacular spoken in Gaeltacht
                        areas. On the other hand, Ó Rinn's Irish was a second language which some
                        native speakers found inelegant. "Rosc Catha na nÓglach", T. F. O'Rahilly's
                        translation, was used by Conradh na Gaeilge in the early 1920s; in 1924,
                        Padraig de Burca said it "deserves more favour than it has received". Other
                        translations included one sung by Claisceadal in University College Galway
                        in December 1931, and others by Pádraig Mac Cárthaigh, Sean Dubhthaigh,
                        Seamus Mac Grianna, and Ernest Blythe. From the 1930s, the Gaelic Athletic
                        Association (GAA) encouraged singing the anthem in Irish at its matches. The
                        text of the Ó Rinn version was printed in 1933 in An Camán, and in the
                        programs of GAA matches at Croke Park, where the crowd was led via the
                        public address system by singers from St Patrick's College of Education and
                        Conradh na Gaeilge. Also in 1933 Eamonn O'Neill suggested in the Dáil that
                        schoolchildren should be taught the words in both English and Irish. In 1935
                        Charles Bewley, Irish envoy to Germany, requested Irish lyrics because "the
                        English text ... makes a bad impression abroad". Both the English and Irish
                        texts appeared in various editions of Facts about Ireland, published by the
                        Department of Foreign Affairs, and on the official website of the Department
                        of the Taoiseach. However, no Irish version has been officially adopted, the
                        state does not hold the copyright to any Irish version, and Ó Rinn, unlike
                        Kearney and Heeney's estate, never received royalties. A memorandum in the
                        Department of the Taoiseach on 5 April 1958 discussed five distinct Irish
                        translations, noting that Ó Rinn's was the best known; it suggested that, if
                        it were to be officially endorsed, the spelling and grammar should be
                        standardised and the opening words "Sinne Fianna Fáil" changed to "Sinne
                        laochra Fáil" to avoid association with the Fianna Fáil political party. The
                        2018 Seanad report on the anthem recommended no change to the wording, and
                        pointed out that the law would not prevent a new political party adopting
                        revised words like "Laochra Fáil" as its name. </p>
                    <p> The English version has been almost totally eclipsed, and many are unaware
                        that the Irish lyrics are a translation. In 1960 it was remarked that the
                        anthem's effect at Croke Park was impaired by the fact that some people sang
                        in English and others in Irish. The Irish Times reported audience
                        participation at a 1962 concert in the Olympia Theatre, Dublin under the
                        headline "Sang National Anthem in Irish". In the 21st century the English
                        version is still sung at home matches of Celtic F.C., a Glasgow Irish-Scots
                        football club. It was sung in Canada during a state visit by President Mary
                        McAleese in 1998, and at the 2004 Ryder Cup in the United States. The latter
                        prompted objections from Fáilte Ireland, and what Gaeltacht Minister Éamon Ó
                        Cuív called "an outcry" from viewers in Ireland. The 2018 Seanad report
                        suggested that "For those not familiar with the Irish language, it may be
                        appropriate to produce a phonetic version of the National Anthem". Some
                        foreign-born Irish international sportspeople have learned the Irish words
                        via ad-hoc phonetic versions, including Mick McCarthy of the association
                        football team and C. J. Stander of the rugby union team. In 1987, the anthem
                        was recommended, but not required, to be taught as part of the civics
                        syllabus in national schools. Fianna Fáil's manifesto in the 2007 general
                        election promised to "nclude the national anthem in the primary school
                        curriculum". As of 2017 the primary school Social Personal and Health
                        Education curriculum includes being "aware" of the anthem in third/fourth
                        class, and "respecting" it in fifth/sixth class. Richard Bruton, the
                        Minister for Education stated that it was "not Departmental policy to impose
                        regulations on schools regarding national expression", but that it had
                        supported several initiatives which included the national anthem. To mark
                        the 2016 centenary of the Easter Rising, members of the Defence Forces
                        visited each national school and presented it with a national flag and
                        copies of the national anthem and the 1916 Proclamation. A 2017 opinion poll
                        found 82% supported teaching the anthem in school; 40% claimed to know all
                        the words and 40% "some" of them. The 2018 Seanad report said the anthem was
                        "indeed currently on the curriculum at primary school level. However, once
                        it has been taught at primary school level there are little opportunities
                        for students to use the National Anthem within the school environment". It
                        said suggestions to sing the anthem at school every day "may not be
                        possible", but school children could be encouraged to sing it on the eve of
                        Saint Patrick's Day. Although only the chorus forms the official national
                        anthem, the music of both verse and chorus has often been played at sports
                        events outside Ireland. The text of the first verse appears as well as the
                        chorus in early (1960s) editions of the Department of External Affairs's
                        book Facts About Ireland. Later editions include only the chorus. The song
                        is used by many Irish nationalists as an anthem for the entire island of
                        Ireland. As such it is played at all GAA matches, including those in
                        Northern Ireland and overseas. The 2018 Seanad report on the anthem
                        recommended awareness of the anthem among "Irish citizens at home and
                        abroad, as well as new citizens of Ireland". It was common in the twentieth
                        century, and not unknown today, for a music session in a pub to end at
                        closing time with the playing of the national anthem. A 1961 Evening Herald
                        editorial complained that the anthem was played "far too often" and "usually
                        in a most undignified manner", and that it "should be limited to very
                        special occasions". There is no protocol specified for the anthem; the 2018
                        Seanad report on the anthem recommended adopting one and provided a draft.
                        The flag protocol issued by the Department of the Taoiseach states that when
                        the anthem is played in the presence of the national flag, all present
                        should face the flag and stand to attention, and Defence Forces personnel
                        should salute the flag, "until the last note of the music". History
                        professor Caoimhín De Barra comments, "I don't think I have ever seen anyone
                        salute the flag during Amhrán na bhFiann. Certainly, nobody is standing to
                        attention until the last note of music, given that we have effectively
                        replaced the last line of the song with collective freestyle screaming and
                        roaring." In 2017, the Seanad Public Consultation Committee invited comments
                        on "the most appropriate way the State should treat the National Anthem".
                        Its chair, Mark Daly, said, "The debate around this issue includes aspects
                        of copyright law, cultural tolerance, respect for national symbols, public
                        opinion, free speech and a range of other factors." The committee heard
                        public submissions from selected commenters on 5 December 2017. Michael W.
                        D'Arcy said the government favoured guidelines rather than legislation, and
                        that penalties for misuse might prove counterproductive. The committee's
                        report was published in July 2018; it recommended producing an official
                        translation into Irish Sign Language (ISL). A deaf choir performed an ISL
                        version of the anthem in Leinster House at the report's official launch. In
                        January 2019, Fianna Fáil senators introduced a private member's bill "to
                        confirm that the choral refrain, with or without the lyrics, of 'Amhrán na
                        bhFiann' or, in the English Language, 'The Soldier's Song' is and continues
                        to be the National Anthem; to provide for a version of the National Anthem
                        in the Irish Sign Language; to confirm that the Presidential Salute is and
                        continues to be the music of the first 4 bars, followed by the last 4 bars,
                        of the National Anthem". </p>
                    <p> In the 1933 Dáil debate on the state's acquisition of the song's copyright,
                        there was discussion of its merits or lack thereof. Frank MacDermot said,
                        'Leaving out sentiment, I must confess, from both a literary and a musical
                        point of view, I would regard the "Soldier's Song" as, shall we say, a
                        jaunty little piece of vulgarity, and I think we could have done a lot
                        better.' Thomas F. O'Higgins responded, "National Anthems come about, not
                        because of the suitability of the particular words or notes, but because
                        they are adopted generally by the nation. That is exactly how the "Soldier's
                        Song" became a National Anthem in this country. It happened to be the Anthem
                        on the lips of the people when they came into their own and when the
                        outsiders evacuated the country and left the insiders here to make the best
                        or the worst of the country. It was adopted by the people here before ever
                        it was adopted by the Executive Council". The Irish Independent in 2016
                        found it "difficult to understand ... how Peadar Kearney, who was ... a
                        splendid poet, could have written such a lacklustre piece." The Irish
                        version is a free translation of the English; in particular, "Sinne Fianna
                        Fáil" is not a literal translation of "Soldiers are we". Fianna Fáil,
                        variously translated as "Soldiers of Destiny", "Warriors of Fál", "Warriors
                        of Destiny", "The Irish Army", or "Soldiers of Ireland", Éamon de Valera
                        regarded the phrase's untranslatability as a virtue. This is from the Irish
                        Fianna ("band of warriors") of Fál (a coronation stone, and metonymically
                        "Ireland"). As an Irish name for the Irish Volunteers, it was an alternative
                        to Óglaigh na hÉireann. The initials "FF" appeared on the Volunteer badge,
                        and remain on that of Irish Defence Forces as successor to the Volunteers.
                        On 2 April 1926, "Fianna Fáil" was chosen as the name of Éamon de Valera's
                        new political party. Ó Rinn's version appeared in a 1927 volume of poetry
                        with a foreword by de Valera. Since the Irish version of the anthem became
                        popular in the 1930s, there has been intermittent resentment of the party
                        name's occurring in it. Publishers Browne and Nolan printed a version in
                        1938 substituting "Sinne laochra Fáil" for "Sinne Fianna Fáil" (laochra,
                        "heroes", "warriors"), which is occasionally heard instead. TD Maureen
                        O'Sullivan likewise favoured changing to "laochra Fáil". In the Dáil in 2011
                        and 2012, she asked the Minister for Finance Michael Noonan whether "Sinne
                        Fianna Fáil" was "appropriate and correct" or had "party political
                        connotations"; Noonan stated it was appropriate and had no such
                        connotations, given that the translation predated the party's founding. The
                        2018 Seanad report on the anthem took the same view. Mícheál Ó Súilleabháin
                        said the Irish lyrics sound worse than the English ones, which rhyme and so
                        are easier to learn. Ulster unionists regard the anthem as specific to the
                        Republic of Ireland, not symbolic of the whole island of Ireland, and
                        deprecate its use with United Ireland symbolism as irredentism. (The
                        symbolism of flags in Northern Ireland raises similar issues.) In 1933, the
                        unionist government invoked its Special Powers Act to ban public display of
                        the tricolour when "representing the Irish Republican Army ... an Irish
                        Republic ... or... any ... unlawful association"; the order was interpreted
                        as a ban in all circumstances unless flown explicitly to represent the Free
                        State. Similar orders specifically banning "The Soldier's Song" were drafted
                        before the 1935 Westminster and 1938 Stormont elections, but the government
                        felt they were too controversial to implement; a general order against music
                        "likely to lead to a breach of the peace" was often invoked when "The
                        Soldier's Song" was played. After the Northern Ireland peace process, when
                        unionists and Conservatives began attending GAA matches in their official
                        capacity, they arrived after the playing of "Amhrán na bhFiann", including
                        sports minister Edwin Poots in 2008, First Minister Peter Robinson in 2012,
                        and Northern Ireland Secretary James Brokenshire in 2017. Robinson's
                        successor Arlene Foster stood for the anthem at the 2018 Ulster Football
                        Final, which was played in the Republic. F. Gunther Eyck's survey of
                        national anthems classifies "Amhrán na bhFiann" under "resistance anthems",
                        alongside "La Marseillaise", "A Portuguesa", and "Poland Is Not Yet Lost".
                        The lyrics been criticised by some commentators for alleged outdatedness,
                        militarism, and anti-British sentiment. Others deny such faults or attribute
                        them to national anthems generally. Kevin Myers described calls for it to be
                        amended or replaced as "seasonal as spring". Questions in the Dáil have been
                        asked by Frank MacDermot in 1932; Noel Lemass in 1973; Trevor Sargent in
                        1993; Derek McDowell in 1995; and John Browne in 2000. Commentators on the
                        1929 Trinity College incident suggested "The Soldier's Song" would be an
                        impediment to closer ties between the Free State and Northern Ireland. The
                        executive of arts body Aosdána rejected a 1989 proposal by Aloys Fleischmann
                        to campaign for a change of anthem, on the basis that it was a political
                        rather than an artistic question. In 1995, during the Northern Ireland peace
                        process, Taoiseach John Bruton suggested at the Forum for Peace and
                        Reconciliation that the anthem be changed, with Fianna Fáil and Sinn Féin
                        disagreeing. The Forum drafted an unpublished report on "obstacles to
                        reconciliation in the Republic"; 1998 newspaper articles summarising the
                        draft claimed it suggested "the government could commission alternative
                        anthems for sporting and other non-official occasions" which were not
                        "excessively militaristic". Fergus Finlay in 2007 suggested "retiring [the
                        anthem] with honour". A 2017 opinion poll found 84% supported retaining the
                        anthem, while 10% favoured replacing it. Historian Fearghal McGarry suggests
                        the fact that the lyrics are no longer sung in English dampens demand for
                        change: "public unfamiliarity with Peadar Kearney's original words has
                        almost certainly extended his song's shelf life as the national anthem". In
                        a debate during the 2011 presidential election, candidates were asked
                        whether the anthem was "fit for purpose". Most acknowledged strong public
                        attachment to it. Martin McGuinness and Dana Rosemary Scallon opposed any
                        change. Mary Davis said people "shouldn’t consider changing it lightly".
                        Michael D. Higgins suggested the Constitutional Convention could discuss the
                        matter. Seán Gallagher had "mixed views" and was "open to explore revising
                        it". David Norris said other anthems were more "blood-thirsty". The 2018
                        Seanad report on the anthem recommended no change to the wording. </p>
                    <p> The previous anthem used by Irish nationalists was "God Save Ireland", with
                        words written by Timothy Daniel Sullivan in 1867 to the tune of "Tramp!
                        Tramp! Tramp!", an American Civil War song written in 1864 by George
                        Frederick Root. "God Save Ireland" commemorated the Manchester Martyrs,
                        executed in 1867 for felony murder for their part in an Irish Republican
                        Brotherhood ambush, and it quickly replaced the previous unofficial anthem,
                        "A Nation Once Again", written in 1845 by Thomas Davis of the Young Ireland
                        movement. "God Save Ireland" was associated with the Irish Parliamentary
                        Party and its eclipse by "The Soldier's Song" after 1916 mirrored the
                        party's eclipse by Sinn Féin. The Irish Rugby Football Union (IRFU) and
                        Ireland national rugby union team are all-island bodies with many unionist
                        supporters; although "Amhrán na bhFiann" is played at Ireland matches in the
                        Republic, it is not played elsewhere, and unionist players are not expected
                        to sing it. During the Troubles, no anthem was played at matches outside
                        Ireland. In Paris, "The Last Rose of Summer" was played in 1929, and before
                        the 1931 match the Department of External Affairs advised ambassador Gerald
                        O'Kelly de Gallagh that, if the organisers refused to allow "The Soldier's
                        Song", then "appropriate Irish airs would be 'St. Patrick's Day', 'The Last
                        Rose of Summer' or 'Let Erin Remember'". At the inaugural Rugby World Cup,
                        captain Donal Lenihan objected that all other teams would have an anthem. At
                        the last minute before the side's opening match in Athletic Park,
                        Wellington, a James Last cassette recording of "The Rose of Tralee" was
                        borrowed from Phil Orr; the music and poor recording quality attracted much
                        criticism and no anthem was played for later matches. At the 1991 World Cup,
                        there was no anthem away to Scotland, Ireland's only game outside Dublin.
                        For the 1995 World Cup in South Africa, the IRFU decided to commission a
                        song from Phil Coulter. His composition, "Ireland's Call", has since been
                        played alongside "Amhrán na bhFiann" at matches within the Republic, and on
                        its own elsewhere, including in Northern Ireland. Other all-island teams
                        have adopted "Ireland's Call" for similar reasons to the IRFU's. The men's
                        and women's hockey teams adopted it in 2000, having previously used the
                        "Londonderry Air"; however, a first-ever Olympic qualification saw the
                        Olympic Council of Ireland standard "Amhrán na bhFiann" used at Rio 2016.
                        Some sports use no anthem, including badminton and bowls. Criticism that
                        "Ireland's Call" was uninspiring prompted The Irish Times to commission a
                        jocular "alternanthem" from The Duckworth Lewis Method for Saint Patrick's
                        Day 2010. A recording of "O'Donnell Abú" was played for the Irish
                        showjumping team at a 1937 competition in Paris; ambassador Art O'Brien
                        threatened a diplomatic incident since the other teams' anthems had been
                        played by a military band. The organisers had been unable to locate a copy
                        of the score, and the Irish embassy had only a piano arrangement. The same
                        air was chosen by the women's hockey team for a 1951 away match against the
                        Netherlands. "The Fields of Athenry" was adopted as a terrace chant by Irish
                        fans at the 1990 FIFA World Cup and later by fans of the rugby team. It has
                        been described as a "de facto national sporting anthem" and "unofficial
                        national anthem". Music The air is of a style comparable with British
                        marches and songs of the era. Colm Ó Lochlainn said, "The tune is not Irish;
                        it sounds to me something between a Sousa march and a German regimental
                        song". It is usually sung or played in march time. Different tempos may be
                        used, however, and the verse and chorus are occasionally played. In 1926 the
                        radio orchestra of 2RN was found too small for an adequate rendition, so a
                        recording by the New York "Fighting Irish" 69th Infantry was soon adopted,
                        prompting complaints that it was too jazz-influenced. A 1961 Evening Herald
                        editorial complained that the anthem was "usually played without any
                        arrangement and often at a tempo more suggestive of a jig tune than an
                        anthem". Fritz Brase's 1930 arrangement was replaced for Defence Forces
                        bands in the 1980s by one by Colonel James R. McGee which simplified the
                        high woodwind parts. Raidió Teilifís Éireann (RTÉ), the Irish national
                        broadcasting company, played an orchestral version in a slow tempo at the
                        close of transmission from 1962 onwards. This was produced by Gerard Victory
                        and arranged by Brian Boydell (who disliked the tune) on the advice of a
                        Canadian consultant who said, "I wan’ it BIG! I envisage the kind of music
                        that will stir the hearts of the Irish people". Boydell's version replaced
                        one by John Francis Larchet introduced in 1954. A special arrangement
                        incorporating traditional Irish instruments was played instead during Easter
                        Week 1966, to mark the 50th anniversary of the Easter Rising. There was
                        negative comment at the lively tempo used in the ceremony for Michelle
                        Smith's gold medals at the 1996 Olympics. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="ga">
                    <p>Is é Amhrán na bhFiann (Béarla: The Soldiers' Song) amhrán náisiúnta na
                        hÉireann. Scríobh Peadar Ó Cearnaigh na liricí, agus chum Patrick Heaney an
                        port. Ba i mBéarla a scríobhadh na liricí ar dtús, ach is é an leagan
                        Gaeilge is gnách a chloisteáil inniu. Ní chantar ach an curfá de ghnáth agus
                        is ar éigean go bhfuil an chuid eile den amhrán ar eolas ag duine ar bith.
                        Tá blas láidir Ghaeilge na Mumhan ar na líricí, agus is minic nach féidir an
                        fonn a choinneáil ach an t-amhrán a chanadh sa chanúint seo. Mar shampla,
                        nuair a chantar ar ardaibh sléibhe, is gá an -bh- san fhocal sléibhe a bhá
                        go hiomlán, mar a dhéantar leis an -bh-/-mh- i nGaeilge na Mumhan ar lorg an
                        ghuta fhada. Nóta tráchta: duan: dán Óglách: Is athfhoirm fhileata den
                        fhocal Óglach é Óglách. Úsáidtear an fhoirm sin anseo ar dhá chúis: 1) ní
                        mór -á- fada a bheith ann le rím a choinneáil leis an bhfocal táid, agus 2)
                        ní mór an bhéim a chur ar an dara siolla, ar mhaithe leis an meadracht.
                        tíocht in áit "teacht", leis an rím a choinneáil le sinn canaídh: is mar
                        "canaig" nó "canaíg" a fhuaimnítear é, mar is gnách i gCúige Mumhan fé:
                        fuaimniú Muimhneach an réamhfhocail úd faoi do ráinig: is minic a chantar a
                        tháinig anseo inniu, nó is iomaí Gaeilgeoir nach dtuigeann an focal
                        "ráinig". Briathar uireasach é "ráinig" (nó "do ráinig" i gCúige Mumhan) a
                        chiallaíonn "shroich" nó "tharla", agus is ar éigean a úsáidtear in aon
                        fhoirm eile é seachas aimsir chaite. Cuid de sheanchaint na Mumhan is ea an
                        briathar "ráinig", agus d'fheicfeá sa litríocht Bhlascaodach é. Uaireanta,
                        caitear leis mar a bheadh "ráinigh" ann (ós rud é gurb ionann "ráinig" agus
                        "ráinigh" san fhuaimniú), agus cruthaítear foirmeacha cosúil le "ráineoinn"
                        (a chiallaíonn "shroichfinn"). a théam: "téimis" an chiall atá leis an
                        bhfoirm sa choimhthéacs seo, ar ndóigh. An fhoirm a úsáidtear anseo, áfach,
                        is é modh foshuiteach na haimsire láithrí é. Sa mhodh seo, úsáidtear tamhan
                        na haimsire láithrí, ach tagann na hiarmhíreanna ón aimsir fháistineach, ach
                        amháin go bhfágtar -f-, -ó-, nó -eo- na haimsire fáistiní ar lár. An iarmhír
                        sin -am, níl sí beo inniu ach i nGaeilge na Mumhan, cf. ragham (Gaeilge na
                        Mumhan) in áit rachaidh muid nó rachaimid an Chaighdeáin. fé lámhach na
                        bpiléar: cuir an bhéim ar an -é- san fhocal piléar. buadhach: is minic a
                        fheictear "buachach" anseo i gcóipeanna doiléire nó mílitrithe den téacs,
                        ach is léir gur buadhach, leagan seanlitrithe den aidiacht buach atá ann.
                        iompáil: leagan Muimhneach den iompú (nó iompó, mar a déarfadh an tUltach).
                        Tháinig "iompáil" díreach ón gcanúint a chleacht Peadar Ua Laoghaire ina
                        úrscéal Séadna. námhad: caithfidh tú an -mh- a bhá go hiomlán ar lorg an -a-
                        fhada,. mar a dhéantar i gcanúint na Mumhan: i gcoinne ná'd. bíobha: namhaid
                        agaibh: béim ar an dara siolla, mar a dhéantar i gCúige Mumhan </p>
                </div>
            </front>
            <body>
                <div type="song" xml:lang="ga">
                    <lg n="1" type="verse">
                        <l n="1">Seo dhíbh, a chairde, duan Ógláigh</l>
                        <l n="2">Caithréimeach bríomhar ceolmhar</l>
                        <l n="3">Ár dtinte cnámh go buacach táid</l>
                        <l n="4">'S an spéir go mín réaltógach</l>
                        <l n="5">Is fonnmhar faobhrach sinn chun gleo</l>
                        <l n="6">'S go tiúnmhar glé roimh thíocht don ló</l>
                        <l n="7">Fé chiúnas chaomh na hoíche ar seol</l>
                        <l n="8">Seo libh, canaídh Amhrán na bhFiann.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="9">Sinne Fianna Fáil,</l>
                        <l n="10">atá faoi gheall ag Éirinn,</l>
                        <l n="11">Buíon dár slua</l>
                        <l n="12">thar toinn do ráinig chugainn,</l>
                        <l n="13">Faoi mhóid bheith saor</l>
                        <l n="14">Seantír ár sinsear feasta,</l>
                        <l n="15">Ní fhágfar faoin tíorán ná faoin tráill.</l>
                        <l n="16">Anocht a théam sa bhearna bhaoil,</l>
                        <l n="17">Le gean ar Ghaeil, chun báis nó saoil,</l>
                        <l n="18">Le gunna-scréach faoi lámhach na bpiléar,</l>
                        <l n="19">Seo libh canaig' amhrán na bhFiann. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="2" type="verse">
                        <l n="20">Cois bánta réidhe, ar ardaibh sléibhe</l>
                        <l n="21">Ba bhuadhach ár sinsir romhainn</l>
                        <l n="22">Ag lámhach go tréan fén sárbhrat séin</l>
                        <l n="23">'Tá thuas sa ghaoth go seolta</l>
                        <l n="24">Ba dhúchas riamh dár gcine cháidh</l>
                        <l n="25">Gan iompáil siar ó imirt áir</l>
                        <l n="26">'S ag siúl mar iad i gcoinne námhad</l>
                        <l n="27">Seo libh, canaídh Amhrán na bhFiann</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="28">Sinne Fianna Fáil,</l>
                        <l n="29">atá faoi gheall ag Éirinn,</l>
                        <l n="30">Buíon dár slua</l>
                        <l n="31">thar toinn do ráinig chugainn,</l>
                        <l n="32">Faoi mhóid bheith saor</l>
                        <l n="33">Seantír ár sinsear feasta,</l>
                        <l n="34">Ní fhágfar faoin tíorán ná faoin tráill.</l>
                        <l n="35">Anocht a théam sa bhearna bhaoil,</l>
                        <l n="36">Le gean ar Ghaeil, chun báis nó saoil,</l>
                        <l n="37">Le gunna-scréach faoi lámhach na bpiléar,</l>
                        <l n="38">Seo libh canaig' amhrán na bhFiann. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="3" type="verse">
                        <l n="39">A bhuíon nach fann d'fhuil Ghaeil is Gall</l>
                        <l n="40">Sin breacadh lae na saoirse</l>
                        <l n="41">Tá sceimhle 's scanradh i gcroíthe námhad</l>
                        <l n="42">Roimh ranna laochra ár dtíre</l>
                        <l n="43">Ár dtinte is tréith gan spréach anois</l>
                        <l n="44">Sin luisne ghlé sa spéir anoir</l>
                        <l n="45">'S an bíobha i raon na bpiléar agaibh</l>
                        <l n="46">Seo libh, canaídh Amhrán na bhFiann</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="47">Sinne Fianna Fáil,</l>
                        <l n="48">atá faoi gheall ag Éirinn,</l>
                        <l n="49">Buíon dár slua</l>
                        <l n="50">thar toinn do ráinig chugainn,</l>
                        <l n="51">Faoi mhóid bheith saor</l>
                        <l n="52">Seantír ár sinsear feasta,</l>
                        <l n="53">Ní fhágfar faoin tíorán ná faoin tráill.</l>
                        <l n="54">Anocht a théam sa bhearna bhaoil,</l>
                        <l n="55">Le gean ar Ghaeil, chun báis nó saoil,</l>
                        <l n="56">Le gunna-scréach faoi lámhach na bpiléar,</l>
                        <l n="57">Seo libh canaig' amhrán na bhFiann. </l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div type="song" xml:lang="en">
                    <lg n="1" type="verse">
                        <l n="1">We'll sing a song, a soldier's song</l>
                        <l n="2">With cheering, rousing chorus</l>
                        <l n="3">As round our blazing fires we throng</l>
                        <l n="4">The starry heavens o'er us</l>
                        <l n="5">Impatient for the coming fight</l>
                        <l n="6">And as we wait the morning's light</l>
                        <l n="7">Here in the silence of the night</l>
                        <l n="8">We'll chant a soldier's song</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="9">Soldiers are we,</l>
                        <l n="10">whose lives are pledged to Ireland,</l>
                        <l n="11">Some have come</l>
                        <l n="12">from a land beyond the wave,</l>
                        <l n="13">Sworn to be free,</l>
                        <l n="14">no more our ancient sireland,</l>
                        <l n="15">Shall shelter the despot or the slave.</l>
                        <l n="16">Tonight we man the "bearna bhaoil",</l>
                        <l n="17">In Erin's cause, come woe or weal,</l>
                        <l n="18">'Mid cannons' roar and rifles' peal,</l>
                        <l n="19">We'll chant a soldier's song. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="2" type="verse">
                        <l n="20">In valley green, or towering crag</l>
                        <l n="21">Our fathers fought before us</l>
                        <l n="22">And conquered 'neath the same old flag</l>
                        <l n="23">That's proudly floating o'er us</l>
                        <l n="24">We're children of a fighting race</l>
                        <l n="25">That never yet has known disgrace</l>
                        <l n="26">And as we march, the foe to face</l>
                        <l n="27">We'll chant a soldier's song</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="28">Soldiers are we,</l>
                        <l n="29">whose lives are pledged to Ireland,</l>
                        <l n="30">Some have come</l>
                        <l n="31">from a land beyond the wave,</l>
                        <l n="32">Sworn to be free,</l>
                        <l n="33">no more our ancient sireland,</l>
                        <l n="34">Shall shelter the despot or the slave.</l>
                        <l n="35">Tonight we man the "bearna bhaoil",</l>
                        <l n="36">In Erin's cause, come woe or weal,</l>
                        <l n="37">'Mid cannons' roar and rifles' peal,</l>
                        <l n="38">We'll chant a soldier's song. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="3" type="verse">
                        <l n="39">Sons of the Gael! Men of the Pale!</l>
                        <l n="40">The long-watched day is breaking</l>
                        <l n="41">The serried ranks of Innisfail</l>
                        <l n="42">Shall set the tyrant quaking</l>
                        <l n="43">Our camp fires now are burning low</l>
                        <l n="44">See in the east a silv'ry glow</l>
                        <l n="45">Out yonder waits the Saxon foe</l>
                        <l n="46">So chant a soldier's song</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg n="Chorus" type="refrain">
                        <l n="47">Soldiers are we,</l>
                        <l n="48">whose lives are pledged to Ireland,</l>
                        <l n="49">Some have come</l>
                        <l n="50">from a land beyond the wave,</l>
                        <l n="51">Sworn to be free,</l>
                        <l n="52">no more our ancient sireland,</l>
                        <l n="53">Shall shelter the despot or the slave.</l>
                        <l n="54">Tonight we man the "bearna bhaoil",</l>
                        <l n="55">In Erin's cause, come woe or weal,</l>
                        <l n="56">'Mid cannons' roar and rifles' peal,</l>
                        <l n="57">We'll chant a soldier's song. </l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
</teiCorpus>
